I love learning foreign languages.
ฉันชอบเรียนภาษาต่างประเทศมาก
In fact, I love it so much that I like to learn a new language every two years,
อันที่จริง ฉันชอบมากถึงขั้นว่า ฉันเรียนภาษาใหม่ทุก ๆ สองปี
currently working on my eighth one.
ตอนนี้ฉันกำลังเรียนภาษาที่แปด
When people find that out about me, they always ask me,
พอใครรู้เข้าก็มักจะถามฉันเสมอว่า
"How do you do that? What's your secret?"
"คุณทำได้อย่างไร มีเคล็ดลับอะไรรึเปล่า"
And to be honest, for many years, my answer would be,
เอาจริง ๆ เลยนะ ฉันก็ตอบแบบนี้มาหลายปีแล้ว
"I don't know. I simply love learning languages."
"ไม่รู้สิ ฉันก็แค่ชอบเรียนภาษา"
But people were never happy with that answer.
แต่ทุกคนก็ไม่พอใจกับคำตอบนั้นเท่าไร
They wanted to know why they are spending years trying to learn even one language,
พวกเขาอยากรู้ว่าทำไม พวกเขาใช้เวลาหลายปี ในการเรียนแค่ภาษาเดียว
never achieving fluency,
แล้วก็ยังไม่คล่องสักที
and here I come, learning one language after another.
แล้วทีฉัน เรียนภาษาแล้วภาษาเล่า
They wanted to know the secret of polyglots,
พวกเขาอยากรู้เคล็ดลับของผู้รู้หลายภาษา
people who speak a lot of languages.
หมายถึงคนที่พูดได้หลายภาษา
And that made me wonder, too,
ก็เลยทำให้ฉันสงสัยด้วยว่า
how do actually other polyglots do it?
จริง ๆ แล้วผู้รู้หลายภาษาคนอื่น เขาทำอย่างไร
What do we have in common?
พวกเรามีอะไรที่เหมือนกัน
And what is it that enables us
และอะไรที่ทำให้เรา
to learn languages so much faster than other people?
เรียนภาษาได้เร็วกว่าคนทั่วไป
I decided to meet other people like me and find that out.
ฉันตัดสินใจไปหาคำตอบ จากคนอื่น ๆ ที่เหมือนกับฉัน
The best place to meet a lot of polyglots
ที่ที่ดีที่สุดในการพบผู้รู้หลายภาษา
is an event where hundreds of language lovers
ก็คืองานที่บรรดาผู้ที่หลงใหลในภาษา
meet in one place to practice their languages.
มาพบปะกันเพื่อฝึกฝนภาษาต่าง ๆ
There are several such polyglot events organized all around the world,
มีงานของผู้รู้หลายภาษาแบบนี้ จัดขึ้นทั่วโลกเลยค่ะ
and so I decided to go there
ฉันเลยตัดสินใจไปร่วมงาน
and ask polyglots about the methods that they use.
และถามถึงวิธีที่พวกเขาใช้
And so I met Benny from Ireland,
ฉันได้พบเบนนี่จากไอร์แลนด์
who told me that his method is to start speaking from day one.
เขาบอกฉันว่าวิธีการเรียนของเขาคือ เริ่มด้วยการสนทนาตั้งแต่วันแรกเลย
He learns a few phrases from a travel phrasebook
เขาเรียนสองสามวลีจาก หนังสือสอนภาษาท่องเที่ยว
and goes to meet native speakers
และก็ไปหาเจ้าของภาษา
and starts having conversations with them right away.
และเริ่มสนทนากับพวกเขาทันที
He doesn't mind making even 200 mistakes a day,
เขาไม่สนว่าจะพูดผิดเป็นร้อย ๆ ครั้งต่อวัน
because that's how he learns, based on the feedback.
เพราะนั่นคือวิธีเรียนของเขา เรียนจากคำชี้แนะ
And the best thing is, he doesn't even need to travel a lot today,
และสิ่งที่เจ๋งสุดคือ เขาไม่ต้องเดินทางบ่อยเลย
because you can easily have conversations with native speakers
เพราะคุณสามารถพูดคุยกับเจ้าของภาษา
from the comfort of your living room, using websites.
ได้สบาย ๆ ในห้องนั่งเล่นผ่านเว็บไซต์
I also met Lucas from Brazil
ฉันยังได้เจอลูคัสจากบราซิล
who had a really interesting method to learn Russian.
เป็นคนที่มีวิธีเรียนภาษารัสเซีย ได้อย่างน่าสนใจมาก
He simply added a hundred random Russian speakers on Skype as friends,
เขาแค่สุ่มเพิ่มเพื่อนชาวรัสเซีย เป็นร้อย ๆ คนใน Skype
and then he opened a chat window with one of them
แล้วก็เปิดแชทคุยกับหนึ่งในนั้น
and wrote "Hi" in Russian.
และทักไปว่า "สวัสดี" เป็นภาษารัสเซีย
And the person replied, "Hi, how are you?"
เขาก็ตอบกลับมาว่า "สวัสดี เป็นไงบ้าง"
Lucas copied this and put it into a text window with another person,
ลูคัสก็คัดลอกข้อความนี้และส่งไปให้อีกแชท
and the person replied, "I'm fine, thank you, and how are you?"
เขาก็ตอบกลับมาว่า "สบายดี ขอบคุณ แล้วคุณล่ะ"
Lucas copied this back to the first person,
ลูคัสก็จะคัดลอกข้อความนี้ และส่งกลับไปให้คนแรก
and in this way, he had two strangers have a conversation with each other
และด้วยวิธีนี้ ทำให้คนแปลกหน้าสองคนคุยกัน
without knowing about it.
โดยที่พวกเขาไม่รู้เรื่องนี้เลย
(Laughter)
(เสียงหัวเราะ)
And soon he would start typing himself,
และในไม่ช้าเขาก็เริ่มพิมพ์เองได้
because he had so many of these conversations
เพราะเขาทำแบบนี้มาเยอะแล้ว
And then I met polyglots who always start by imitating sounds of the language,
แล้วฉันก็ได้รู้จักกับผู้รู้หลายภาษา ที่เริ่มเรียนโดยการเลียนเสียง
and others who always learn the 500 most frequent words of the language,
และคนที่เริ่มเรียน โดยท่องคำศัพท์ที่พบบ่อย 500 คำ
and yet others who always start by reading about the grammar.
และคนที่เริ่มเรียนโดยศึกษาไวยากรณ์ก่อน
If I asked a hundred different polyglots,
ถ้าฉันถามผู้รู้หลายภาษาหลายร้อยคน
I heard a hundred different approaches to learning languages.
ฉันคงได้หลายร้อยวิธีในการเรียนภาษา
Everybody seems to have a unique way they learn a language,
เหมือนว่าทุกคนต่างมีวิธีเรียน ที่จำเพาะเป็นของตัวเอง
and yet we all come to the same result of speaking several languages fluently.
แล้วทุกคนก็ได้ผลลัพธ์เหมือนกัน คือพูดหลายภาษาได้อย่างคล่องแคล่ว
And as I was listening to these polyglots telling me about their methods,
พอได้ฟังพวกเขาพูดถึงวิธีเรียนของตัวเอง
it suddenly dawned on me:
ฉันก็เข้าใจได้ในทันทีได้ว่า
the one thing we all have in common
สิ่งหนึ่งที่เรามีเหมือนกันก็คือ
is that we simply found ways to enjoy the language-learning process.
เราแค่สนุกไปกับกระบวนการเรียนภาษา
All of these polyglots were talking about language learning
พวกเขากำลังพูดถึงการเรียนภาษา
as if it was great fun.
ให้เหมือนกับการเล่นสนุก
You should have seen their faces
คุณน่าจะได้เห็นสีหน้าของพวกเขา
when they were showing me their colorful grammar charts
ตอนเขาเอาแผนผังไวยกรณ์หลากสีให้ฉันดู
and their carefully handmade flash cards,
และการ์ดช่วยจำที่ทำเองอย่างประณีต
and their statistics about learning vocabulary using apps,
และสถิติการเรียนคำศัพท์ในแอปต่าง ๆ
or even how they love to cook based on recipes in a foreign language.
หรือแม้กระทั่งการอ่าน ตำราอาหารภาษาต่างประเทศ
All of them use different methods,
ทุกคนใช้วิธีที่ต่างกัน
but they always make sure it's something that they personally enjoy.
แต่พวกเขาเลือกในวิธีที่พวกเขา
I realized that this is actually how I learn languages myself.
ฉันตระหนักได้ว่า ที่จริงแล้ว นี่แหละคือวิธีที่ฉันเรียนภาษา
When I was learning Spanish, I was bored with the text in the textbook.
ตอนที่ฉันกำลังเรียนภาษาสเปน บทความในหนังสือเรียนน่าเบื่อมาก
I mean, who wants to read about Jose
คือใครจะไปอยากอ่านเรื่องพวกนั้นล่ะ
asking about the directions to the train station. Right?
เรื่องถามทางไปสถานีรถไฟอะไรแบบนั้น
I wanted to read "Harry Potter" instead,
ฉันอยากอ่าน "แฮรี่ พอตเตอร์" มากกว่า
because that was my favorite book as a child,
เพราะเป็นหนังสือเล่มโปรดตั้งแต่เด็กแล้ว
and I have read it many times.
และฉันก็อ่านมาแล้วหลายรอบแล้วด้วย
So I got the Spanish translation of "Harry Potter" and started reading,
ฉันก็เลยหาหนังสือแฮรี่ พอตเตอร์ ที่แปลภาษาสเปนและเริ่มอ่านมัน
and sure enough, I didn't understand almost anything at the beginning,
แล้วก็เป็นไปตามคาด ในตอนแรก ฉันแทบจะไม่เข้าใจอะไรสักอย่างเลย
but I kept on reading because I loved the book,
แต่ฉันก็อ่านไปเรื่อย ๆ เพราะชอบหนังสือเล่มนี้
and by the end of the book, I was able to follow it almost without any problems.
และพออ่านจบเรื่องแล้ว ฉันก็เข้าใจได้โดยไม่มีปัญหาอะไร
And the same thing happened when I was learning German.
ตอนเรียนภาษาเยอรมัน ก็เป็นอย่างนี้เหมือนกัน
I decided to watch "Friends," my favorite sitcom, in German,
ฉันดูหนังเบาสมองเรื่องโปรดอย่าง "Friends" เป็นภาษาเยอรมัน
and again, at the beginning it was all just gibberish.
แล้วก็เหมือนเดิม ตอนแรก ฉันไม่เข้าใจอะไรเลย
I didn't know where one word finished and another one started,
ฉันไม่รู้ว่าคำไหนเป็นคำไหน
but I kept on watching every day because it's "Friends."
แต่ฉันก็ดูต่อไปเรื่อย ๆ เพราะมันคือ "Friends"
I can watch it in any language. I love it so much.
ฉันจะดูเรื่องนี้เป็นภาษาอะไรก็ได้ เพราะฉันชอบมาก
And after the second or third season,
และหลังจบภาคสองหรือสามนี่แหละ
seriously, the dialogue started to make sense.
จริง ๆ นะ ฉันก็เริ่มเข้าใจบทสนทนาแล้ว
I only realized this after meeting other polyglots.
ฉันก็เพิ่งมาคิดได้ก็ตอนเจอ ผู้รู้หลายภาษาคนอื่นนี่แหละ
We are no geniuses
พวกเราไม่ใช่อัจฉริยะ
and we have no shortcut to learning languages.
พวกเราไม่มีทางลัดในการเรียนภาษา
We simply found ways how to enjoy the process,
เราแค่เจอหนทางที่จะสนุกไปกับการเรียน
how to turn language learning from a boring school subject
เปลี่ยนการเรียนภาษา จากวิชาเรียนที่น่าเบื่อ
into a pleasant activity which you don't mind doing every day.
ไปเป็นกิจกรรมแสนสนุก ที่คุณไม่เกี่ยงที่จะทำในทุก ๆ วัน
If you don't like writing words down on paper,
ถ้าคุณไม่ชอบการเขียนลงบนกระดาษ
you can always type them in an app.
คุณพิมพ์ลงในแอปก็ได้
If you don't like listening to boring textbook material,
ถ้าคุณไม่ชอบฟังบทเรียน ที่แสนน่าเบื่อจากตำรา
find interesting content on YouTube or in podcasts for any language.
หายูทูบหรือพอดแคสต์ ภาษาอะไรก็ได้ที่คุณสนใจฟังสิคะ
If you're a more introverted person
ถ้าคุณเป็นคนโลกส่วนตัวสูง
and you can't imagine speaking to native speakers right away,
และคุณคิดไม่ออกว่า จะคุยกับเจ้าของภาษาได้อย่างไร
you can apply the method of self-talk.
คุณก็ลองเปลี่ยนมาเป็นการพูดกับตัวเอง
You can talk to yourself in the comfort of your room,
คุณจะคุยกับตัวเองในห้องสบาย ๆ อย่างไรก็ได้
describing your plans for the weekend, how your day has been,
บรรยายถึงแผนในช่วงสุดสัปดาห์ หรือเล่าว่าวันนี้เป็นอย่างไรบ้าง
or even take a random picture from your phone
หรือแม้กระทั่งสุ่มรูปจากโทรศัพท์
and describe the picture to your imaginary friend.
แล้วอธิบายภาพนั้น ให้เพื่อนในจินตนาการฟังก็ได้
This is how polyglots learn languages,
นี่เป็นวิธีที่ผู้รู้หลายภาษาเขาทำกัน
and the best news is, it's available to anyone
และข่าวดีก็คือ ใคร ๆ ก็สามารถทำได้
who is willing to take the learning into their own hands.
ถ้าเขาเต็มใจจะเอาวิธีเหล่านี้ไปใช้
So meeting other polyglots helped me realize
ดังนั้นการได้เจอพวกเขา ช่วยทำให้ฉันคิดได้ว่า
that it is really crucial to find enjoyment
การหาความสนุกในกระบวนการเรียนภาษา
in the process of learning languages,
เป็นสิ่งที่สำคัญมาก
but also that joy in itself is not enough.
แต่แค่ความสนุกอย่างเดียวก็คงจะไม่พอ
If you want to achieve fluency in a foreign language,
ถ้าคุณอยากพูดภาษาต่างประเทศ ได้อย่างคล่องแคล่วแล้วล่ะก็
you'll also need to apply three more principles.
คุณจะต้องใช้หลักการอีกสามข้อ
First of all, you'll need effective methods.
ข้อแรก ต้องใช้วิธีที่มีประสิทธิภาพ
If you try to memorize a list of words for a test tomorrow,
ถ้าคุณพยายามจะจำศัพท์ชุดหนึ่ง เพื่อใช้สอบในวันพรุ่งนี้
the words will be stored in your short-term memory
คำศัพท์ก็จะถูกเก็บไว้ ในหน่วยความจำระยะสั้นเท่านั้น
and you'll forget them after a few days.
แล้วหลังจากนั้นสองสามวันคุณก็จะลืม
If you, however, want to keep words long term,
แต่ถ้าคุณอยากจำศัพท์ให้ได้นาน ๆ
you need to revise them in the course of a few days repeatedly
คุณต้องทบทวนศัพท์นั้นซ้ำ ๆ ไปมา ในช่วงสองสามวัน
using the so-called space repetition.
ใช้วิธีการทำซ้ำแบบเว้นระยะ
You can use apps which are based on this system such as Anki or Memrise,
คุณสามารถใช้แอปที่ใช้หลักการนี้ อย่างเช่น Anki หรือ Memrise
or you can write lists of word in a notebook using the Goldlist method,
หรือคุณสามารถเขียนศัพท์ลงใน สมุดบันทึกโดยใช้วิธี Goldlist
which is also very popular with many polyglots.
ซึ่งนิยมมากในหมู่ผู้รู้หลายภาษา
If you're not sure which methods are effective and what is available out there,
ถ้าไม่แน่ใจว่ามีวิธีไหนบ้าง และวิธีไหนถึงจะได้ผลดีที่สุด
just check out polyglots' YouTube channels and websites
ลองเข้าไปหาเว็บหรือช่องยูทูป ของผู้รู้หลายภาษา
and get inspiration from them.
ไปหาแรงบันดาลใจจากพวกเขา
If it works for them, it will most probably work for you too.
ถ้าเขาทำแล้วได้ผล คุณก็อาจจะทำแล้วได้ผลเช่นกัน
The third principle to follow
หลักการที่สามคือ
is to create a system in your learning.
จัดการรูปแบบในการเรียนของคุณ
We're all very busy and no one really has time to learn a language today.
ทุกวันนี้เราทุกคนก็ต่างยุ่ง และไม่มีเวลามาเรียนภาษากัน
But we can create that time if we just plan a bit ahead.
แต่เราแบ่งเวลาได้ ถ้าวางแผนล่วงหน้าสักหน่อย
Can you wake up 15 minutes earlier than you normally do?
คุณจะยอมตื่นเช้ากว่าปกติ สัก 15 นาทีไหม
That would be the perfect time to revise some vocabulary.
คงเป็นเวลาที่เหมาะมาก สำหรับทบทวนคำศัพท์
Can you listen to a podcast on your way to work while driving?
คุณจะยอมฟังพอดแคสต์ ระหว่างขับรถไปทำงานไหม
Well, that would be great to get some listening experience.
นั่นก็ยิ่งดีเลยที่ได้จะฝึกฟัง
There are so many things we can do without even planning that extra time,
ยังมีอีกหลายอย่างที่เราสามารถทำได้ โดยไม่ต้องหาเวลาว่างเพิ่ม
such as listening to podcasts on our way to work
อย่างเช่นการฟังพอดแคสต์ ระหว่างขับรถไปทำงาน
or doing our household chores.
หรือตอนทำงานบ้าน
The important thing is to create a plan in the learning.
ที่สำคัญคือ การวางแผนในการเรียน
"I will practice speaking every Tuesday and Thursday
"ฉันจะฝึกพูดทุก ๆ วันอังคารกับพฤหัส
with a friend for 20 minutes.
กับเพื่อนเป็นเวลา 20 นาที
I will listen to a YouTube video while having breakfast."
ฉันจะดูยูทูบตอนทานข้าวเช้า"
If you create a system in your learning,
ถ้าคุณจัดการรูปแบบในเรียนของคุณ
you don't need to find that extra time,
คุณก็ไม่ต้องไปหาเวลาว่างเพิ่ม
because it will become a part of your everyday life.
เพราะมันจะกลายเป็นส่วนหนึ่ง ในชีวิตประจำวัน
And finally, if you want to learn a language fluently,
และสุดท้ายถ้าคุณอยากเรียน ภาษาให้ได้คล่อง ๆ
you need also a bit of patience.
คุณจะต้องมีความอดทนสักหน่อย
It's not possible to learn a language within two months,
เป็นไปไม่ได้หรอกที่เราจะเรียน และเป็นเลยภายในเดือนสองเดือน
but it's definitely possible to make a visible improvement in two months,
แต่แน่นอนว่าเราจะเห็นพัฒนาการ ได้ภายในสองเดือน
if you learn in small chunks every day in a way that you enjoy.
ถ้าคุณเก็บเล็กผสมน้อยทุก ๆ วัน เรียนในแบบที่คุณชอบ
And there is nothing that motivates us more
ไม่มีอะไรที่กระตุ้นเราได้มากกว่า
than our own success.
ความสำเร็จของตัวเอง
I vividly remember the moment
ฉันจำได้ชัดเจนถึงตอนนั้น
when I understood the first joke in German when watching "Friends."
ที่ฉันเข้าใจมุกแรกในภาษาเยอรมัน ตอนดู "Friends"
I was so happy and motivated
ฉันดีใจมากและมีแรงบันดาลใจ
that I just kept on watching that day two more episodes,
ที่จะดูต่อไปอีกสองตอนในวันนั้น
and as I kept watching,
เมื่อดูไปเรื่อย ๆ
I had more and more of those moments of understanding, these little victories,
ฉันก็เข้าใจมากขึ้นเรื่อย ๆ เป็นชัยชนะเล็ก ๆ
and step by step, I got to a level where I could use the language
ทำให้ฉันก้าวไปทีละขั้นสู่ระดับที่สามารถ
freely and fluently to express anything.
ใช้ภาษาในการแสดงความคิดเห็น ได้อย่างอิสระและคล่องแคล่ว
This is a wonderful feeling.
มันเป็นความรู้สึกที่ดีมาก
I can't get enough of that feeling,
เป็นความสุขที่ไม่มีที่สิ้นสุด
and that's why I learn a language every two years.
นี่ก็คือเหตุผลที่ฉัน เรียนภาษาใหม่ทุก ๆ สองปี
So this is the whole polyglot secret.
ทั้งหมดนี้เป็นเคล็ดลับของผู้รู้หลายภาษา
Find effective methods which you can use systematically
หาวิธีที่มีประสิทธิภาพ ซึ่งคุณสามารถใช้อย่างเป็นระบบ
over the period of some time in a way which you enjoy,
ในช่วงเวลาที่คุณจัดการได้ ในรูปแบบที่คุณชื่นชอบ
and this is how polyglots learn languages within months, not years.
และนี่ก็คือวิธีที่ผู้รู้หลายภาษาใช้เรียนได้สำเร็จ ในหลักเดือนและไม่ถึงปี
Now, some of you may be thinking,
ถึงตอนนี้ บางคนอาจคิดว่า
"That's all very nice to enjoy language learning,
"มันก็ดีนะที่สนุกไปกับการเรียนภาษา
but isn't the real secret that you polyglots
แต่เคล็ดลับที่แท้จริงของพวกรู้หลายภาษา
Well, there's one thing I haven't told you about Benny and Lucas.
ยังมีบางอย่างเกี่ยวกับเบนนี่และลูคัส ที่ฉันไม่ได้บอกพวกคุณ
Benny had 11 years of Irish Gaelic and five years of German at school.
เบนนี่เรียนภาษาไอริชมาตั้ง 11 ปี และเรียนภาษาเยอรมันที่โรงเรียนมา 5 ปี
He couldn't speak them at all when graduating.
แต่พอเรียนจบเขากลับพูดไม่ได้เลย
Up to the age of 21, he thought he didn't have the language gene
จนถึงอายุ 21 เขาคิดว่า คงเป็นเพราะเขาไม่มียีนเก่งภาษา
and he could not speak another language.
และเขาคงพูดภาษาอื่นไม่ได้ด้วย
Then he started to look for his way of learning languages,
จากนั้นเขาก็เริ่มหาวิธีการเรียน ในแบบของเขาเอง
which was speaking to native speakers and getting feedback from them,
ก็คือการพูดกับเจ้าของภาษา และเรียนรู้จากคำชี้แนะ
and today Benny can easily have a conversation in 10 languages.
และตอนนี้เบนนี่สามารถสนทนา ได้ตั้ง 10 ภาษาได้อย่างง่ายดาย
Lucas tried to learn English at school for 10 years.
ส่วนลูคัสก็พยายามเรียนภาษาอังกฤษ ที่โรงเรียนมาเป็นเวลา 10 ปี
He was one of the worst students in class.
เขาเป็นหนึ่งในพวกนักเรียนยอดแย่ของห้อง
His friends even made fun of him
ขนาดเพื่อนยังล้อ
and gave him a Russian textbook as a joke
แกล้งเขาด้วยการเอาหนังสือภาษารัสเซียให้
because they thought he would never learn that language, or any language.
เพราะเพื่อน ๆ คิดว่า เขาคงไม่มีทางเรียนรัสเซียหรือภาษาอื่นได้
And then Lucas started to experiment with methods,
แล้วลูคัสก็เริ่มทดลองหาวิธีการเรียน
looking for his own way to learn,
ในรูปแบบของตัวเขาเอง
for example, by having Skype chat conversations with strangers.
อย่างเช่นคุย Skype กับคนแปลกหน้า
And after just 10 years,
และหลังจากนั้นแค่ 10 ปี
Lucas is able to speak 11 languages fluently.
ลูคัสสามารถพูดได้ 11 ภาษา อย่างคล่องแคล่ว
Does that sound like a miracle?
นั่นฟังดูเหมือนปาฏิหาริย์ใช่ไหมคะ
Well, I see such miracles every single day.
ฉันเห็นปาฏิหาริย์แบบนี้มาแล้วในทุกวัน
As a language mentor,
ในฐานะที่ปรึกษาด้านภาษา
I help people learn languages by themselves,
ฉันช่วยให้คนเรียนภาษาด้วยตัวเอง
and I see this every day.
และฉันก็เห็นเรื่องแบบนี้ทุกวัน
People struggle with language learning for five, 10, even 20 years,
ผู้คนพยายามใช้เวลาเพื่อการเรียนภาษา 5 ปีบ้าง 10 ปีบ้าง หรือกระทั่ง 20 ปีก็มี
and then they suddenly take their learning into their own hands,
แต่เมื่อพวกเขาเริ่มเรียนรู้ในแบบของตัวเอง
start using materials which they enjoy, more effective methods,
เริ่มใช้สื่อที่พวกเขาชอบ ซึ่งเป็นวิธีที่มีประสิทธิภาพมากกว่า
or they start tracking their learning
หรือเริ่มติดตามผลการเรียนรู้
so that they can appreciate their own progress,
เพื่อที่พวกเขาจะได้ปลื้มใจ กับความก้าวหน้าของตัวเอง
and that's when suddenly
และตอนนั้นเองพวกเขาก็ได้ค้นพบ
they magically find the language talent that they were missing all their lives.
พรสรรค์ทางภาษาที่พวกเขาไม่เคยมีมาทั้งชีวิต ได้อย่างน่าอัศจรรย์
So if you've also tried to learn a language
ดังนั้นถ้าคุณได้ลองเรียนภาษา
and you gave up, thinking it's too difficult
และคุณยอมแพ้เพราะคิดว่ามันยากเกินไป
or you don't have the language talent,
หรือคิดว่าคุณไม่มีพรสรวรรค์ในการเรียนภาษา
give it another try.
ลองพยายามอีกครั้งหนึ่ง
Maybe you're also just one enjoyable method away
บางทีคุณกำลังจะได้ค้นพบวิธีการสนุก ๆ
from learning that language fluently.
ที่จะทำให้คุณใช้ภาษาได้อย่างคล่องแคล่ว
Maybe you're just one method away from becoming a polyglot.
บางทีการจะจะได้เป็นผู้รู้หลายภาษา กำลังอยู่ใกล้แค่เอื้อมแล้ว
Thank you.
ขอบคุณค่ะ
(Applause)
(เสียงปรบมือ)